Guide to the Robert A. Burt Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert A. Burt papers
1978-2015
MS 2052
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.75
17 boxes and 1 flash drive.
The Robert A. Burt papers contain correspondence and class materials created and collected by Professor Robert A. Burt (LAW 64) during his tenure as Professor of Law at Yale Law School. These papers are directly related to his professional activities and do not contain personal papers. These papers span the years of 1974-2015.
Burt, Robert A., 1939-2015
Biographical / Historical
Robert "Bo" Burt (1939-2015), LAW 1964, was a Yale Law School Professor Emeritus and a member of the faculty of Yale Law School. He recieved his BA from Princeton (1960) and his MA in Jurisprudence from Oxford (1962), followed by his JD from Yale Law School (1964). In 1976 he joined the faculty of Yale Law School after teaching at the University of Michigan and the University of Chicago.
Robert Burt's primary area of study was bioethics and the law, as well as the relationship between the Bible and the law. He taught courses at Yale Law such as "Medicine Ethics" and "The Book of Job and Injustice". He wrote six books over the course of his career, including "Take Care of Strangers: The Rule of Law in Doctor-Patient Relations" and "In the Whirlwind: God and Humanity in Conflict."
Robert Burt passed away in 2015.
Scope and Contents
The Robert A. Burt papers contain correspondence and class materials created and collected by Professor Robert A. Burt (LAW 64) during his tenure as Professor of Law at Yale Law School. These papers are directly related to his professional activities and do not contain personal papers. These papers span the years of 1974-2015.
Arrangement
The Robert A. Burt Papers are arranged in two series: I. Correspondence, 1976-1986. II, Course materials 1970-2015.
Conditions Governing Access
The Restricted Correspondence folders are restricted to researcher access due to FERPA regulations and cannot be accessed until January 1, 2062.
Computer files that are located in the course materials series are restricted to researcher access until the digital processing of these materials is complete.
Separated Materials
Photocopied and published course materials have mostly been removed, unless not described in course overviews.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Linda R. Burt, 2015.
Law -- Study and teaching; Lawyers -- United States -- 20th Century; Medical ethics; Religion and law; Burt, Robert A., 1939-2015; Yale Law School
- Correspondence, 1976-1986; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The Correspondence series contains the professional correspondence of Professor Robert Burt during his tenure at Yale Law from the years of 1976-1986.
  Arrangement
  The Correspondence series is organized chronologically.
  - 1976 July - December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1977 January - April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1977 May - December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1978 January - March (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1978 April - September (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1978 October - December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1978 November - December (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1979 January - June (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1979 July - December (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1980 January - June (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1980 July - December (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1980 July - December (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1981 January - May (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - 1981 June - December (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1983 June - September (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1982 December (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1983 January - March (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1983 April (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1983 November - December (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1984 January - March (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1984 April - July (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1984 August - December (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1985 January (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - 1985 January - June (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1985 July - December (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1986 January - April (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1986 April - July (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1986 August - November (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1986 November (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Restricted correspondence
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted due to FERPA until January 1, 2062.
    - 1978 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - 1981 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - 1983 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - 1985 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - 1986 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Course materials, 1970-2015; Series II
  The Course Materials series contains lists of courses and lists of materials used by Professor Burt during his tenure as a professor. Published material listed in the course materials have been removed. This series dates from 1970-2015.
  The Course Materials series is arranged alphabetically, and then chronologically for courses taught more than once.
  Computer files are restricted to researcher access until they have been fully processed.
  - Administering Death
    - Spring 1993 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1995 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Advocacy for People with Disabilities
    - 1994 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Articles and course materials, 1988-1990 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Bioethics and the Law, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Biotechnology and Anti-social Conduct: Controlling the Controller lecture, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - The Book of Job and Injustice, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Children in the Law
    - 1983 (Box 8, Folder 5-7)
  - The Constitutional Case for Same-Sex Marriage lecture, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Constitutional Law I
    - 1987 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - 1988 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1990 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1991 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - The Constitution, the Supreme Court, and the Concept of Authority in American Political Life
    - 1986-1988 (Box 9, Folder 4-6)
  - Courts, Congress, and the Constitution, Undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Dependency and the Law
    - 1979 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - 1981 (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
  - Family and the Law, 1978 January (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Family Law
    - 1995 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - 1995 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Adult relations
      - Circa 1980 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - 1998 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - 2001 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Take home test, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - General
    - Articles and course materials
      - Circa 1990 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
      - Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Computer files, 2014-2015; 2016-M-071-0001; 1 (Box 18)
      Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
      Closed until processed.
  - Health Policy, Politics, and Law, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
  - Holocaust Testimonies, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Legal and Psychoanalytic Perspectives on Attorney-client Relation, 1982 September (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Legal Control of Biomedical Sciences
    - Fall 1976 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
    - Winter 1976 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
  - The Legislative Process, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Materials on the Selective Service System, Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Medicine, Ethics, and Law
    - 1999 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Yale-New Haven Teachers Institute seminar materials, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
  - Multiculturalism on the Law, Undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Prisoners and Experimentation, Undated (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
  - Professional Conduct in Law and Medicine, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Psychoanalytic and Legal Perspectives on Attorney-client Relations, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Psychoanalysis and Violence, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Regulating Birth, Extending Life, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Regulating Physician-patient Relations, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Representing Clients
    - Undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - 1980 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Representing People with Disabilities, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Rights of Disabled People, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
  - Selected Topics in Comparative Constitutional Law, 1987 July (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Seminar of the United States Congress, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
  - Slavery, the Constitution, and the Supreme Court
    - 1980 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - 1982 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - 1982 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1983 (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
    - 1983 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Stability, Change, and the Law, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - The Supreme Court in American Political History Yale National Teachers Institute 2006 seminar (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - The Urban Public School System, Undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Disability Rights, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Memorandum by Mr. Justice Jackson, Undated (Box 16, Folder 2)